A Guide to the Vera Jansone Drawings ca 1940s, 1961-75
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Vera Jansone Drawings ca 1940s, 1961-75
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
9.5 cu. ft., 4 oversize folders, 9 oversize boxes.
Vera Jansone, by way of Inge Horton, donated material in 2000 and in 2003. This collection is part of the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA) and is housed in the Special Collections Department of the University Library, Virginia Tech.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Latvia, Vera Jansone studied architecture, engineering, and art history at the University of Latvia. Following World War II, Jansone left her homeland to accept a scholarship to study at the Ecole des Beaux Arts from 1945-49, after which she worked full time in the Atelier Le Corbusier on the reconstruction of Paris. Upon receiving her French license, Jansone started practicing with J.L. Humbaire working mostly on schools, housing, hospitals and commercial buildings. In 1950 Jansone was awarded full tuition and travel expenses under an American Association of University Women (AAUW) scholarship to attend the Illinois Institute of Technology, where she studied under Mies van der Rohe. Jansone received her MS in Architecture from IIT in 1952.
After returning briefly to Paris, Jansone moved to the United States, first living in New York for a short duration and later moving with her husband to California in the early 1960s, where job opportunities were much more abundant for women architects. Some of her projects include The Fox Plaza while working with Victor Gruen Associates; underground stations for the Bay Area Rapid Transit (BART) system while working with Ernest Born; the Mt Shasta Mall in Redding CA while working at Robert B. Liles, Inc.; and the Sycamore Medical Building, while working with T. Liles & Assoc.
Scope and Content Information
The Vera Jansone collection consists of 89 drawings documenting her career as a student at the Ecole Nationale Superieure des Beaux Arts, Paris and as a professional architect in California. Her student work is comprised of drawings of the Atelier Labro, Atelier Perret, and Atelier Auguste Perret. Her later work includes drawings from the Mount Shasta Mall in Redding, CA, Commercial Development in Vancouver, WA, and Pearl Ridge Shopping Mall in Honolulu, HI. Also included are drawings from the Del Norte Medical Center, BART Civic Center, Crescent Beach, CA renderings, Fox Plaza Rapid Transit, and various stations and parks in San Francisco. Additionally, the collection contains an article in the "OWA Tour of Residences Designed by Women Architects in Marin County and Napa Valley" about the Greenbrae Residence which Jansone designed in 1975, as well as two resumes.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically according to project.
Contents List
- Vera Jansone Architectural Drawings ca 1940s, 1961-74
  - Atelier Labro (9 drawings) ca. 1940s (Oversize 1)
  - Atelier Auguste Perret (10 drawings) ca. 1940s (Oversize 2)
  - Atelier Perret (7 drawings) ca. 1940s (Oversize 3)
  - Del Norte Medical Center (12 drawings) 1961, n.d. (Folder 1)
  - Fox Plaza, San Francisco, 8.5.1963 (3 drawings) Crescent Beach Recreation Center, CA, 1964 (4 drawings) (Folder 2)
  - BART Civic Center, San Francisco, 1965 (1 drawing) BART Bosworth Station, 1964-65 (3 drawings) BART Glen Park Station, 1968 (2 drawings) BART Balboa Park Street, 1968 (1 drawing) (Folder 3)
  - Mt. Shasta Mall, Redding, CA, 1973 (10 drawings) Pearl Ridge Phase Two, 1974 (1 drawing) Commercial Development, Vancouver, WA, 1974 (1 drawing) Unidentified drawing, n.d. (1 drawing) (Folder 4)
  - BART Bosworth Station (7 drawings) 1965, n.d. (Oversize 4)
  - BART Bosworth Station, Mission Street Line (2 drawings) 1965 (Oversize 5)
  - BART Civic Center Station (3 drawings) 1965 (Oversize 6)
  - BART Civic Center Station (4 drawings) 1965 (Oversize 7)
  - BART Glen Park Station (4 drawings) 1967-68 (Oversize 8)
  - BART Market Street, Montgomery Station - 1964 (1 drawing) BART Market Street, Civic Center Station - 1965 (1 drawing) BART Balboa Park - 1963 (1 drawing) Commercial Development, Vancouver, WA - 1974 (1 drawing) 1963-74 (Oversize 9)